I want to take a moment to talk about something that's very fundamental to an LLM, which is the number
LLM의 아주 근본적인 것에 대해 잠시 얘기하고 싶습니다 LLM 매개
of parameters that sits inside the LLM parameters, also called weights.
변수 안에 있는 매개 변수의 수입니다 웨이트라고도 하죠
Generally, parameters and weights are synonymous.
보통 매개변수와 무게는 동의어예요
There is a detail that they're not exactly the same in some situations.
어떤 상황에서는 완전히 다른 세부 사항이 있어요
But but basically think of weights and parameters as the same thing.
하지만 기본적으로 중량과 매개 변수는 같아요
Model weights.
모델 웨이트예요
These are the levers that are within a model that controls what kinds of outputs it generates when it's
이건 모델 안에 있는 레버로 입력을 받았을 때 출력을 생성하는 것을 통제하죠
How does it go about predicting the next word that's going to follow.
다음에 나올 단어를 어떻게 예측하시나요?
And these weights are weights that are set when you train an LLM.
이 웨이트는 LLM 훈련 때 쓰는 거예요
It sees lots and lots of examples, and it uses those examples to shift around its weights until it
수많은 예시를 보고 그 예시를 이용해 무게를 움직입니다 상태가
gets better and better at predicting the next thing to come out the next token.
더 좋아져서 다음 토큰에서 나올 것을 예측할 수 있을 때까지요
We'll talk about tokens in a minute, but it gets better and better at that.
토큰에 대해 곧 얘기하겠지만 점점 더 재미있어지죠
And the way it gets better is by adjusting all of its weights.
모든 무게를 조정하면 더 좋아지죠
And for some of you that work in data science, this is all stuff you know very, very well for people
데이터 과학을 하는 분들은 처음 보시는 분들에겐 아주 잘 아는
that are new to it.
것들이죠
During the course of the course, we will be looking at this in different ways, so you'll get a better
과정을 진행하는 동안 다양한 방식으로 살펴볼 겁니다 보다 나은 직관력을
and better intuition to what it means to have these parameters, these weights that control the output.
갖게 될 거예요 getput을 제어하는 매개 변수와 저울이 어떤 의미인지를요
But the first thing that one has to come to, to, to realize, to appreciate is how many weights we're
하지만 우선 얼마나 많은 중량이 있는지 알아야 합니다 기존의
talking about and what this means in the days of, of the the simpler of traditional data science,
데이터 과학이나 머신 러닝에서는 단순하게 접근했기 때문에
traditional machine learning, one would build a model such as a linear regression model, which is
선형 회귀 모델이라는 모델을 개발해야 했습니다 가중된 평균을
something which sort of takes like a weighted average, and it would typically have somewhere between
가지고 20에서 200 정도의 매개 변수를 갖습니다
20 and 200 parameters, or weights 20 and 200 is about the range you'd often usually be talking about.
보통 20에서 200 정도의 중량으로 접근하죠
And one of the somewhat bizarre, remarkable thing about these LMS is that we're talking about such
LMS가 특이한 점 중 하나는 무게의 수가 다르다는
a different number of weights.
거예요
GPT one that came out back in 2018, I had 117 million waits.
2018년에 출시된 GPT 1은 1억 1,700만 명이 기다렸어요
Now, this was actually something that was personally galling for me, because at the time we had a
개인적으로 좀 화가 났던 부분인데요 LMS@타입의
deep neural network, of which the LMS at types, we had one in my startup, and I used to go around
딥 신경망이 있었을 때 제 스타트업에 하나 있었는데 딥 신경망에 200,000
showing off that our deep neural network had 200,000 parameters, which I thought was a staggeringly
매개 변수가 있다고 자랑하곤 했어요 엄청나게 큰 숫자라고 생각했죠 200,000
large number, and I couldn't imagine any possibility of a model that had more than 200,000 parameters.
매개 변수가 넘는 모델은 상상할 수도 없었어요
So when GPT one came out with 117 million parameters, I was stumped.
그래서 GPT 1이 매개 변수를 1억 1,700만 개 제시했을 때 당황했죠
It really made me appreciate, uh, how how the enormity of GPT one.
GPT 1의 중요성을 절실히 깨닫게 됐죠
But then, you know, as you can probably see, this, this scale that you're seeing here is a logarithmic
그런데 보다시피 여기 보이는 이 범위는 로그식 범위예요 틱을 켤 때마다
scale, which means that every tick doesn't mean one more notch.
한 단계씩 더 올라가는 게 아니죠
It means ten times the number of parameters as the, as the, as the tick before it.
매개 변수의 10배를 앞의 체크보다 더 많이 입력해야 해요
And let's layer on to this diagram.
이 다이어그램에 레이어를 겹쳐보죠
The subsequent versions of GPT, GPT two with 1.5 billion parameters.
GPT 2의 후속 버전인 1을 추가했죠 50억 개의 매개 변수가 있어요
GPT three 175 billion parameters.
GPT 3,750억 매개 변수예요
I mean, this is just unspeakable.
말로 표현이 안 돼요
Number of parameters.
변수가 많아요
GPT 41.7 6 trillion parameters.
GPT 41요 7조 6천억 매개 변수예요
And then the latest frontier models.
최신 개척 시대 모델도 있죠
They haven't actually announced how many parameters they have.
매개 변수가 몇 개인지 아직 발표하지 않았어요
It is believed that they have around 10 trillion parameters.
약 10조 매개 변수가 있는 것으로 추정되죠
It is an almost unthinkable number of these weights that are running.
이 추의 숫자는 상상할 수 없을 정도예요
Um, and now let's layer on top of this some of the open source models.
이제 이 위에 오픈 소스 모델을 레이어하죠
So Gemma is 2 billion.
제마는 20억 달러예요
It's a lightweight model.
가벼운 모델이에요
And you may also remember that llama 3.2 that we worked on when we were using llama also had 2 billion
라마 3도 기억하실 거예요 라마를 사용할 때 작업했던 2개의 데이터에도 20억 개의 매개
uh parameters.
변수가 있었어요
Uh, then llama 3.1, which is it's it's uh a Bigger Cousin comes in three varieties an 8 billion version,
그럼 라마 3요 1번, 그러니까 더 큰 사촌은 세 종류가 있어요
a 70 billion version, and then llama 3.1 405B, which is the largest of the open source models at this
80억 개, 700억 개 그리고 라마 3이죠 1 405B는 현재 오픈 소스 모델 중 가장 큰
time and which has similar capabilities really to some of the frontier closed source models.
것으로 일부 비공개 소스 모델과 비슷한 기능을 갖고 있죠
And then I mentioned mixed rail here, the mixture of experts model.
혼합 레일도 언급했었죠 전문가들의 혼합 모델이요
So this is just here to give you some insight into how enormous these models are.
이 모델들이 얼마나 거대한지 통찰력을 주는 거예요
And it's hard to even comprehend what it means to have 10 trillion different weights, different sort
10조 개의 무게와 다양한 지렛대 다양한 숫자가 있다는 게 어떤 의미인지 이해하기조차
of levers, different numbers.
어려워요
You can think of them as little knobs within this enormous model that controls the output given an input.
입력된 출력을 조절하는 이 거대한 모델 안의 작은 손잡이라고 생각하면 돼요
And again, compare that in your mind to an old fashioned linear regression model that might have between
그리고 다시 한 번 구식 선형 회귀 모델과 비교해 보세요 20에서 200
20 and 200 parameters.
매개 변수가 있을 거예요
Just to get a sense of the enormity of these large language models.
Get in get 이 거대한 언어 모델의 방대함을 느껴보려고요